The final section in this chapter deals with central nervous system tumors.
CNS tumors can be metastatic or primary.
About 50% are metastatic and 50% are primary.
When you have metastatic lesions,
these usually present as multiple well-circumscribed lesions,
most often at the gray-white junction.
The three most common sources that like to go to the brain
are lung cancer, breast cancer, and kidney cancer.
So those are the big three.
Primary tumors of the central nervous system
are classified according to cell type.
And it's very important to note that when you have a malignant primary tumor,
it's locally destructive.
However, it usually will not spread outside of the central nervous system.
Now again, let's focus on the fact that these are classified according to cell type.
So in order to understand central nervous system tumors,
we really need to understand the normal cells present within the central nervous system.
And so let's just do a very quick overview.
Recall that the central nervous system is comprised of approximately 50% neurons
and 50% glial tissue.
The glial tissue is the tissue that supports the neurons.
It helps to keep the neurons separate.
It helps to maintain the neurons.
And it's sort of the glue of the central nervous system.
Now the glial system includes the astrocytes.
The astrocytes are particularly noteworthy because they form the blood-brain barrier.
It also includes the oligodendrocytes.
And of course, the oligodendrocytes, they myelinate the axons.
And then it also includes the ependymal cells.
And the ependymal cells, they are the cells that line the ventricular spaces.
Of course, the other 50% of the CNS is comprised of the neurons.
And then finally, surrounding the brain, you have meningothelial cells.
Now these are the five key cells in the brain.
And it's these five cells that produce the key tumors within the brain that we need to be aware of.
Now these cells can produce tumors within children or they can produce tumors in adults.
And so with that background in mind, let's go through each of these.
Now astrocytes are the most abundant glial cell.
And the tumor that classically arises from astrocytes in a kid is called the pylocytic astrocytoma.
This is a benign tumor of astrocytes.
And we'll discuss that in more detail as we move forward.
The most common tumor of astrocytes in adults is called the glioblastoma multiforme.
This is a highly malignant tumor of astrocytes.
It's the most common CNS tumor in adults.
Oligodendrocytes form something called an oligodendroglioma.
That's classically seen in adults.
Ependymal cells can form an ependymoma.
This is classically seen in children.
Neurons don't really form tumors because neurons have very limited ability to divide.
Remember that the neurons are a permanent tissue.
And so if you can't divide, it's going to be very hard to produce a tumor, obviously.
However, in children, the neurons do divide.
And the classic tumor that arises from the quote-unquote neurons is something called a medulloblastoma,
which is really a tumor derived from neuroectoderm,
which again is the type of tissue from which the neurons are also derived.
And finally, from the meningothelial cells, you can get a meningioma, and that classically occurs in adult females.
And so this is a little bit of a summary of the types of tumors that we're going to talk about.
And now I want to make one more point before we go into the individual tumors.
And that is that this line here represents the tentorium.
And tumors in adults usually occur above the tentorium,
whereas tumors in kids usually occur beneath the tentorium.
And that's particularly high yield.
The first of the tumors is a glioblastoma multiforme.
Again, this is a malignant high-grade tumor of astrocytes.
It's the most common malignant CNS tumor in adults.
The tumor usually arises in the cerebral hemisphere,
so I'm outlining for you the tumor here.
And one of the very high yield associations with this tumor
is that it crosses this midline structure here called the corpus callosum.
And that's a particularly important feature of glioblastoma multiforme.
Now sometimes people like to call this the butterfly glioma,
and that's sort of because it crosses over like this and gives an image of a butterfly.
And so it's also known as a butterfly glioma.
There are two characteristic features of histology
that are particularly important to know for the purposes of board exams.
The first is that the tumor produces a large amount of necrosis,
and so you can see here that the cells are dying and necrotic.
And then as a result of that necrosis,
the cells that are living or viable end up forming this edge,
to the area of the necrosis.
And because it looks like this edge is lining up against the necrosis,
we call that pseudopalisading.
Remember, palisading means to line up,
but here the cells aren't really lining up.
They simply are the living cells that are at the edge of the necrosis,
and so we call that quote-unquote pseudopalisading.
And so that's one very important histologic feature.
The second important histologic feature
is that you get endothelial cell proliferation,
and that's not shown on this image here,
but it's important to note.
Examiners also like you to note
that this tumor is derived from a glial cell,
and so therefore the intermediate filament present within these cells
will be GFAP.
GFAP is the intermediate filament present within glial cells,
and that also is particularly high yield.
Meningioma is a benign tumor of the arachnoid cells.
It's the most common benign tumor in adults,
classically more often seen in an adult female.
It's important to note, and particularly high yield,
that this tumor expresses estrogen receptor,
and so it's probably estrogen that has some role
in the development of this tumor,
and so that helps us to remember
that it's going to be an adult female
that's going to be the key person
that's going to get this tumor,
especially on an examination.
Now the tumor actually forms a round mass
that's attached to the dura,
and that's what imaging would reveal,
and that round mass will then press on the cortex,
and when it presses on the cortex,
it will create seizures.
Now it's important to note that the tumor compresses,
but does not invade the cortex,
and again, that'll result in seizures.
Here's a classic histology showing the world appearance of cells,
which is sort of the high yield characteristic of this tumor.
Remember that this tumor can also result
in abundant somoma bodies,
and that's because these world cells can calcify,
and when they calcify,
you would get somoma bodies within the tumor.
Now this picture does not show somoma bodies,
but it is important to know
that you get a world pattern of cells with somoma bodies,
and again, that's high yield.
Schwannoma is a tumor that we haven't talked about yet.
It's a benign tumor of Schwann cells,
and Schwann cells, of course,
are the cells that myelinate the peripheral nervous system.
Now this can involve the cranial nerves or the spinal nerves,
and it's especially common involving the eighth cranial nerve
at the cerebellopontine angle,
and so that's why we're including it in this discussion,
because when it arises at the CPA,
that's going to be within the cranium,
and so we're talking about it here
as a central nervous system tumor.
Patients who have eighth cranial nerve schwannomas,
they classically present with a loss of hearing
and tinnitus or ringing in their ears.
It's important to note that the schwannoma is S100 positive.
That's high yield,
and it's also high yield to know
that bilateral schwannomas of the eighth cranial nerve
are seen in neurofibromatosis type 2.
Oligodendrogliomas are malignant tumors
of oligodendrocytes.
The most important association here
is that you get a calcified tumor in the white matter.
Of course, it's the white matter
because that's where the oligodendrocytes are.
They myelinate the axons,
producing the color of the white matter,
and it usually involves the frontal lobe
presenting with seizures,
and so all of this is high yield.
Calcified tumor in the frontal lobe,
arising in the white matter,
and presenting with seizures.
Here's an image of the classic histology.
It's known as the fried egg appearance.
Imagine that this is an egg here.
This is the egg white,
and then the nucleus represents the yolk of the egg.
You can see that there's a bunch of fried eggs
throughout this biopsy.
Again, classic for oligodendroglioma.
Moving on to tumors that most often arise in children,
a pilocytic astrocytoma
is a benign tumor of astrocytes.
It's the most common CNS tumor in children,
and it usually arises in the cerebellum,
but of course we know that
because most tumors in children
are going to be beneath the tentorium.
The classic imaging for a pilocytic astrocytoma
is a cystic lesion with a mural nodule,
or a nodule growing on its wall,
and so this here is the classic imaging.
Now, if you have trouble remembering that,
you can sort of think as pilocytic astrocytoma
as a pilocytic astrocytoma,
if you want to just play with the words,
and then that'll help you to remember
that it's a cyst with a mural nodule,
and again, this is particularly high yield.
When biopsy is performed,
the key finding is that you have astrocytes
with these thick eosinophilic processes,
and these are called Rosenthal fibers,
and Rosenthal fibers are an important
high yield association with a pilocytic astrocytoma.
Now, it's also important to note
that these are astrocytes, which are glial cells,
and so this tumor would also be GFAP positive.
Medulloblastoma is a malignant tumor
derived from the granular cells of the cerebellum.
It's particularly high yield to note
that this tumor is derived
from neural ectodermal tissue.
Board examiners like to ask you that.
It usually arises in children.
The histology reveals small, round blue cells
with homo-right rosettes.
Now, homo-right rosettes are
when the small, round blue cells,
they wrap around pink areas of neuritic processes,
and so we call those homo-right rosettes
because they are forming a rosette
around those neuritic processes.
This tumor has a poor prognosis.
It grows rapidly,
and it can then enter into the fourth ventricular space,
and using the CSF,
it can then drop down to the spinal cord
and involve the cord,
and those are called drop metastases,
and that's also particularly high yield.
Ependymoma is a malignant tumor of the ependymal cells.
Remember that the ependymal cells,
they line the ventricular space.
It's usually seen in children,
and because it's usually seen in children,
it'll be beneath the tentorium,
and beneath the tentorium means
it'll be in the fourth ventricle.
Because this tumor arises from the cells
lining the ventricular space,
it'll eventually grow out into the ventricular space,
and it can block the flow of CSF,
producing hydrocephalus,
and that's very high yield as well.
Here's a picture of the histology of an ependymoma.
The key finding is that
you have perivascular pseudorosettes.
Now here's a blood vessel here,
and you can see that the tumor cells,
these blue cells,
are lining up against this blood vessel
with some pink material in between,
and so we call that a perivascular pseudorosette.
Cranial pharyngioma is a tumor that arises
from the epithelial remnants of Rathke's pouch.
It's particularly high yield
because of its tie-in with embryology.
So let's go back and review.
Recall that if this is the base of the brain,
and this is the floor of the mouth,
then an upward protrusion of the floor of the mouth
results in formation of the anterior pituitary,
and a downward protrusion of the base of the brain
results in formation of the posterior pituitary.
And of course, these will eventually come together
to form the anterior and the posterior pituitary.
And of course, that sits in a space
called the cella tersica.
This is important to note
because this upward protrusion of the floor of the mouth
is called Rathke's pouch,
and eventually it should separate
from the floor of the mouth
and then produce this distinct anterior pituitary.
However, sometimes you can have remnants
of Rathke's pouch that remain along this pathway,
and it's from these remnants
that you can develop something called a cranial pharyngioma.
Now, think about the word cranial means in the cranium,
pharyngi means that you're arising from the pharynx,
and oma refers that you have a mass.
Now, of course, this tissue here,
the remnants of Rathke's pouch,
arose from the upward protrusion of the pharynx.
Now, again, notice that it's sitting here
in the cella tersica,
and it can then produce classic symptoms,
which we'll talk about in a moment.
Okay, so cranial pharyngioma is a tumor
that arises from the epithelial remnants of Rathke's pouch.
It presents as a supratentorial mass,
and again, that's because the cella tersica is supratentorial
in a child or a young adult.
It can compress the optic chiasm,
given its location near the optic chiasm,
which will then result in bitemporal hemianopsia.
Now, very high yield,
because bitemporal hemianopsia,
we sort of always associate with pituitary adenomas,
or tumors of the pituitary gland.
However, it's important to note
that if you have bitemporal hemianopsia,
in a child, you really want to think
about a cranial pharyngioma,
and that's particularly high yield.
Now, this tumor on imaging is often calcified,
and the way I remember this
is that it's derived from the floor of the mouth,
and the floor of the mouth has tooth-like tissue,
and so you can get calcifications on imaging.
The tumor is benign,
but it tends to recur after resection,
and so these are some of the high yield points
concerning cranial pharyngioma,
and that concludes our discussion
of both the section and the chapter.